Guide to the Robert Morris Ogden papers, 1889-1959
Ogden, Robert Morris papers, 1889-1959
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Robert Morris Ogden papers, 1889-1959.
14-23-467
Robert Morris Ogden, 1877-1959.
11.5 c.f.
Correspondence, financial records, notes, essays, drafts, reviews, reprints, Cornelliana, student notebooks, photographs, puzzles, drawings, essays, a mess kit, and other materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, financial records, notes, essays, drafts, reviews, reprints, and printed material pertaining to Ogden's work as a psychologist, author, and educator and to his membership in various scientific societies.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Robert M. Ogden specialized in educational psychology and aesthetics, and served as Dean of the College of Arts and Sciences at Cornell University from 1923 to 1945. He was an early proponent of Gestalt psychology.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence pertaining to Ogden's work as a psychologist, author, and educator and to his membership in various scientific societies. Includes personal and family correspondence; financial records; notes, essays, drafts, reviews, reprints, and printed material on psychology, aesthetics, and philosophy; Cornelliana and student notebooks; photographs; a few small puzzles; accounts of the Mrs. John S. Dorsey estate; and photographs and drawings used in The Psychology of Art. Also, correspondence and essays concerning Andrew Dickson White, his diaries, and the early history of Cornell; and a Civil War mess kit.
Indexes of correspondence available in accession folder.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Ogden, Robert Morris, 1877-1959.; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.; Cornell University--Faculty.; Cornell University--History.
Subjects:
Aesthetics.; Decedents' estates.; Philosophy.; Psychology.; College teachers.; Psychologists.
Places:
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Collectibles.
Form and Genre Terms:
Drawings.; Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Link to a finding aid with an extended list of correspondents.
  All the material in the collection may not be covered by this guide.
- Correspondence
  - Feb. 20, 1889-June 15, 1910 (Box 1)
  - July 4, 1910-June 25, 1913 (Box 2)
  - July 2, 1913-Dec. 19, 1915 (Box 3)
  - Jan. 6, 1916-May 31, 1921 (Box 4)
  - June 2, 1921-June 22, 1925 (Box 5)
  - July 1, 1925-Dec. 25, 1932 (Box 6)
  - Feb. 13, 1933-Mar. 31, 1937 (Box 7)
  - Apr. 1, 1937-June 27, 1939 (Box 8)
  - July 1, 1939-Dec. 31, 1941 (Box 9)
  - Jan. 1, 1942-Dec. 29, 1944 (Box 10)
  - Jan. 1, 1945-Dec. 30, 1947 (Box 11)
  - Jan. 1, 1948-June 30, 1953 (Box 12)
  - July 1, 1953-Feb. 24, 1959 (Box 13)
  - n.d. (Box 14)
- Other materials
  - Income tax returns and other financial records; correspondence; Dorsey estate records; American Psychological Association; poetry; correspondence and drafts of articles about Andrew Dickson White by Robert Morris Ogden. (Box 15)
  - Manuscript and typescript writings; notes; correspondence; miscellany. Topics include aesthetics, hearing, psychology, philosophy, and related subjects. (Box 16)
  - Publications; papers and reviews; American Society of Aesthetics; National Education Association. (Box 17)
  - Manuscript and typescript drafts of Robert Morris Ogden writings. (Box 18)
  - Envelope of metal puzzles; manuscript and typescript drafts of A Book on Aesthetics and other writings; student notebooks of Robert and Helen Ogden; Cornell scrapbook and other memorabilia. (Box 19)
  - Student sketches by Ogden; children's artwork; photographs, photos of paintings and Ogden's transparencies used in analyzing the artworks; and diplomas. (Box 20)
  - Reprints of articles and reviews. (Box 21)
  - Civil War mess kit. (Box 22)